<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<regulation xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs ../../eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2011-07-22</date>
    <originalDate>2012-01-01</originalDate>
    <title>ALTERNATIVE MORTGAGE TRANSACTION PARITY</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1004</section>
    </cfr>
    <effectiveDate>2011-07-22</effectiveDate>
  </preamble>
  <part label="1004">
    <tableOfContents>
      <tocSecEntry target="1004-1">
        <sectionNum>1</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1004.1 Authority, purpose, and scope.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1004-2">
        <sectionNum>2</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1004.2 Definitions.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1004-3">
        <sectionNum>3</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1004.3 Preemption of State law.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1004-4">
        <sectionNum>4</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1004.4 Requirements for alternative mortgage transactions.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocAppEntry target="1004-A">
        <appendixLetter>A</appendixLetter>
        <appendixSubject>Appendix A to Part 1004—Official Commentary on Regulation D</appendixSubject>
      </tocAppEntry>
    </tableOfContents>
    <content>
      <subpart>
        <tableOfContents>
          <tocSecEntry target="1004-1">
            <sectionNum>1</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1004.1 Authority, purpose, and scope.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1004-2">
            <sectionNum>2</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1004.2 Definitions.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1004-3">
            <sectionNum>3</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1004.3 Preemption of State law.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1004-4">
            <sectionNum>4</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1004.4 Requirements for alternative mortgage transactions.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
        </tableOfContents>
        <content>
          <section label="1004-1" sectionNum="1">
            <subject>§ 1004.1 Authority, purpose, and scope.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1004-1-a" marker="(a)">
              <title type="keyterm">Authority.</title>
              <content>Authority. This regulation, known as Regulation D, is issued by the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection to implement the Alternative Mortgage Transaction Parity Act, <ref target="USC:12-3801" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 3801</ref> et seq., as amended by title X, Section 1083 of the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act (Pub. L. 111-203, <ref target="STATUTES_AT_LARGE:124-Stat.-1376" reftype="external">124 Stat. 1376</ref>). Section <ref target="1004-4" reftype="internal">1004.4</ref> is issued pursuant to the Alternative Mortgage Transaction Parity Act (as amended) and the Truth in Lending Act, <ref target="USC:15-1601" reftype="external">15 U.S.C. 1601</ref> et seq.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-1-b" marker="(b)">
              <title type="keyterm">Purpose.</title>
              <content>Purpose. Consistent with the Alternative Mortgage Transaction Parity Act, the Truth in Lending Act, and the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act, the purpose of this regulation is to balance access to responsible credit and enhanced parity between <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">State</ref> and federal <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditors</ref> regarding the making, purchase, and enforcement of <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> with consumer protection and the interests of the <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">States</ref> in regulating mortgage transactions generally.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-1-c" marker="(c)">
              <title type="keyterm">Scope.</title>
              <content>Scope. This regulation applies to an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> if the creditor received an application for that transaction on or after July 22, 2011. This regulation does not apply to a transaction if the creditor received the application for that transaction before July 22, 2011.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <analysis>
              <analysisSection>
                <title>Section 1004.1 Authority, Purpose, Scope</title>
                <analysisParagraph>This section addresses the authority, purpose, and scope of the new Part 1004, which the CFPB is issuing to implement AMTPA, as amended by Section 1083 of the Dodd-Frank Act.</analysisParagraph>
                <analysisSection>
                  <title>(a) Authority</title>
                  <analysisParagraph>Section 1004.1(a) explains that Part 1004 implements AMTPA as amended by Section 1083 of the Dodd-Frank Act, pursuant to the rulemaking authority transferred to the CFPB from various transferor agencies under Section 1061 of the Dodd-Frank Act. This section also explains that § 1004.4 is issued based on the CFPB's authority under TILA.</analysisParagraph>
                </analysisSection>
                <analysisSection>
                  <title>(b) Purpose</title>
                  <analysisParagraph>Consistent with AMTPA, TILA, and the Dodd-Frank Act, § 1004.1(b) states that the purpose of Part 1004 is to balance: (1) Access to responsible credit and enhanced parity between state and federal housing creditors regarding the making, purchase, and enforcement of alternative mortgage transactions, with (2) consumer protection and the interests of the states in regulating mortgage transactions generally. The purpose of AMTPA (as defined in 12 U.S.C. 3801) is to provide parity between federal and state housing creditors “by authorizing all housing creditors to make, purchase, and enforce alternative mortgage transactions so long as the transactions are in conformity with the regulations issued by the Federal agencies.” However, as described above, the level of parity provided by AMTPA has been modified by the Dodd-Frank Act's amendments to the definition of “alternative mortgage transaction” and the scope of preemption under AMTPA, which narrow the range of transactions eligible for AMTPA preemption and restore the effect of certain state mortgage laws. Section 1004.1(b) reflects this modification as well as the CFPB's use of its consumer protection authority under TILA.</analysisParagraph>
                </analysisSection>
                <analysisSection>
                  <title>(c) Scope</title>
                  <analysisParagraph>Section 1004.1(c) states that Part 1004 applies to an alternative mortgage transaction if the creditor received an application for that transaction on or after July 22, 2011. This section further states that Part 1004 does not apply to a transaction if the creditor received the application for that transaction before July 22, 2011.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>Section 1083(c) of the Dodd-Frank Act provides that its amendments to AMTPA do not affect “any transaction covered by the Alternative Mortgage Transaction Parity Act of 1982 (12 U.S.C. 3801 <em data-original="E-03">et seq.</em>) and entered into on or before the designated transfer date.” Accordingly, the CFPB must determine when a transaction is “entered into” for purposes of determining which preemption standards and rules—pre-Dodd-Frank Act amendments or post-Dodd-Frank Act amendments—are applicable. Rather than a single event, a mortgage transaction is a series of steps progressing from application to consummation to servicing. Each of these steps is subject to a variety of state and federal consumer protection statutes, many of which govern activities that occur prior to consummation (such as disclosure and underwriting). In order to establish a workable regulatory regime, there must be a readily identifiable date and a single set of rules to govern the entire transaction. In light of these considerations, the CFPB has interpreted an “alternative mortgage transaction” as being “entered into” on the date the application is received by the creditor. This interpretation seeks to ensure that the entire transaction is governed by a consistent set of rules. For example, if an application for a mortgage transaction is received on July 21, 2011, but is not completed on August 21, 2011, AMTPA preemption is determined under the regime in effect prior to the Dodd-Frank Act amendments. However, if the application is received on July 22, 2011, AMTPA preemption is determined under the regime established by the Dodd-Frank Act amendments and this interim final rule.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>Comment 1(c)-1 clarifies that, if an application for a transaction is received by a creditor prior to July 22, 2011, whether 12 U.S.C. 3803(c) preempts state law with respect to that transaction depends on whether: (1) The transaction was an alternative mortgage transaction as defined by the version of 12 U.S.C. 3802(1) in effect at the time of application; and (2) the state housing creditor complied with applicable federal regulations issued by the OCC, NCUA, or OTS/FHLBB in effect at the time of application.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>Comment 1(c)-2 clarifies that, if 12 U.S.C. 3803(c) or this interim final rule (as applicable) preempted state law at the time an application was received, certain subsequent actions with respect to that transaction are entitled to the same degree of preemption. This comment applies regardless of whether the application was received before, on, or after July 22, 2011. First, if state law was preempted at the time of application, state law is also preempted with respect to the subsequent consummation, completion, purchase, or enforcement of the transaction by a state housing creditor. This interpretation is consistent with 12 U.S.C. 3801(b) and 3803(a), which address state housing creditors' ability to “make, purchase, or enforce” alternative mortgage transactions.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>Second, if state law was preempted at the time of application, state law is also preempted with respect to the subsequent modification, renewal, or extension of the transaction. The CFPB interprets such activity as constituting a continuation of the same “transaction” for purposes of AMTPA. For instance, if a distressed borrower with a variable rate mortgage loan that is currently subject to preemption under AMTPA would be able to avoid foreclosure through a modification, the CFPB believes that AMTPA should continue to preempt state law that would otherwise prohibit the modification. However, if state law was preempted at the time of application and the transaction is later satisfied and replaced by another transaction (such as through a refinancing), the second transaction must independently meet the requirements for preemption in effect at the time the second transaction is made under 12 U.S.C. 3803(c) or this interim final rule (as applicable).</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>This interpretation is generally similar to the statutory language that governed the transition period with regard to states that decided to opt-out of the statutory preemption regime when AMTPA was first enacted.<footnote ref="48">12 U.S.C. 3804(a)(2) (providing that “any renewal, extension, refinancing, or other modification of an alternative mortgage transaction that was entered into during the preemption period” would also be afforded AMTPA preemption).</footnote>
            However, the interim final rule treats refinancings differently than modifications, extensions, and renewals because, as provided in 12 CFR 226.20, a refinancing constitutes a new transaction that satisfies and replaces an existing obligation. Under these circumstances, the CFPB believes that the new transaction should be evaluated independently with respect to AMTPA preemption. The CFPB seeks comment on these interpretations, particularly as to what types of modifications might otherwise be prohibited under state law and whether additional protections are needed with respect to modifications.</analysisParagraph>
                </analysisSection>
              </analysisSection>
            </analysis>
          </section>
          <section label="1004-2" sectionNum="2">
            <subject>§ 1004.2 Definitions.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1004-2-def0" marker="none">
              <content>For purposes of this part:</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-2-a" marker="none">
              <content><def term="alternative mortgage transaction" id="928d2a15bbab2fad46203758ff4e81169172fd2f">Alternative mortgage transaction</def> means a loan, credit sale, or account:</content>
              <paragraph label="1004-2-a-1" marker="(1)">
                <content>That is secured by an interest in a residential structure that contains one to four units, whether or not that structure is attached to real property, including an individual condominium unit, cooperative unit, mobile home, or trailer, if it is used as a residence;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-2-a-2" marker="(2)">
                <content>That is made primarily for personal, family, or household purposes; and</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-2-a-3" marker="(3)">
                <content>In which the interest rate or finance charge may be adjusted or renegotiated.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-2-b" marker="none">
              <content>Creditor shall have the same meaning as in <ref target="CFR:12-226-2" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.2</ref>.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-2-c" marker="none">
              <content><def term="housing creditor" id="2eabed2fb2a0df881069754e8acd218322aede1f">Housing creditor</def> means:</content>
              <paragraph label="1004-2-c-1" marker="(1)">
                <content>A depository institution, as defined in section 501(a)(2) of the Depository Institutions Deregulation and Monetary Control Act of 1980;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-2-c-2" marker="(2)">
                <content>A lender approved by the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development for participation in any mortgage insurance program under the National Housing Act;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-2-c-3" marker="(3)">
                <content>Any person who regularly makes loans, credit sales, or advances on an account secured by an interest in a residential structure that contains one to four units, whether or not the structure is attached to real property, including an individual condominium unit, cooperative unit, mobile home, or trailer, if it is used as a residence; and</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-2-c-4" marker="(4)">
                <content>Any transferee of a party listed in paragraph <ref target="1004-2-c-1" reftype="internal">(c)(1)</ref>, <ref target="1004-2-c-2" reftype="internal">(2)</ref>, or <ref target="1004-2-c-3" reftype="internal">(3)</ref> of this section.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-2-d" marker="none">
              <content><def term="state" id="aa4a5f8125f234182e2dea92805afdfb747a86be">State</def> means any State of the United States of America, the District of Columbia, Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, the Northern Mariana Islands, American Samoa, Guam, and any other territory or possession of the United States.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-2-e" marker="none">
              <content><def term="state law" id="b070ef4a8406d218428a05122c673ff890851f2b">State law</def> means a <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">State</ref> constitution, statute, or regulation or any provision thereof.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <analysis>
              <analysisSection>
                <title>Section 1004.2 Definitions</title>
                <analysisSection>
                  <title>(a) Alternative Mortgage Transaction</title>
                  <analysisParagraph>The interim final rule defines “alternative mortgage transaction” to include a loan, credit sale, or account: (1) That is secured by an interest in a residential structure that contains one to four units, whether or not the structure is attached to real property, including an individual condominium unit, cooperative unit, mobile home, and trailer, if it is used as a residence; (2) that is made primarily for personal, family, or household purposes; and (3) in which the interest rate or finance charge may be adjusted or renegotiated.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>Comment 2(a)-1 clarifies that home equity lines of credit and subordinate lien mortgages are alternative mortgage transactions as long as they meet the definition in § 1004.2(a). Comment 2(a)-2, discussed in more detail below, provides specific examples of transactions that are alternative mortgage transactions, while comment 2(a)-3 provides examples of transactions that are not alternative mortgage transactions.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>The first element of the definition of alternative mortgage transaction is derived from AMTPA as well as the definition of a “dwelling” in 12 CFR 226.2(a)(19). The second element of the definition requires that an alternative mortgage transaction involve an extension of consumer credit. AMTPA's findings indicate that Congress was concerned with the availability of housing credit to consumers.<footnote ref="49">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; 12 U.S.C. 3801(a)(1) (finding that &amp;#8220;increasingly volatile and dynamic changes in interest rates have seriously impaired the ability of housing creditors to provide &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;consumers&lt;/em&gt; with fixed-term, fixed-rate credit secured by interests in real property, cooperative housing, manufactured homes, and other dwellings&amp;#8221; (emphasis added)).</footnote>

            In addition, AMTPA applies to transactions secured by <em data-original="E-03">residential</em> real property or a <em data-original="E-03">dwelling</em> (including stock allocated to a dwelling in a residential cooperative housing corporation or a residential manufactured home). While some consumers may use their residence as security for credit for non-consumer purposes (such as to finance a business), AMTPA's use of the terms “residential” property and “dwelling” indicate that it is intended to apply to alternative mortgage transactions involving consumer credit. In addition, requiring alternative mortgage transactions to be consumer credit aligns the AMTPA regulations with the CFPB's general scope of authority under TILA, which also serves as authority for this interim final rule. However, the CFPB seeks comment on this issue.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>The third element of the definition requires that the interest rate or finance charge for the transaction may be adjusted or renegotiated. As described above, Section 1083 narrows AMTPA's definition of an “alternative mortgage transaction” so that it refers only to loans and credit sales “in which the interest rate or finance charge may be adjusted or renegotiated, [as] described and defined by applicable regulation.” As noted above, Section 1083 deletes language that specifically included within the definition of alternative mortgage transaction: (1) Fixed-rate balloon loans “which implicitly permit[] rate adjustments” because the debt matures before the end of the loan's amortization schedule; and (2) mortgage loans “involving any similar type of rate, method of determining return, term, repayment, or other variation not common to traditional fixed rate, fixed term transactions,” including but not limited to shared equity and shared appreciation transactions.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>The interim final rule construes the amendment to exclude only those mortgages that do not involve an adjustable or renegotiable rate or finance charge. For example, a fixed-rate loan that permits the consumer to make interest-only payments for a period of time does not involve an adjustment to or renegotiation of the interest rate or finance charge. Previously, such transactions were considered alternative mortgage transactions under the third prong of the original AMTPA definition since an interest-only feature was “not common to traditional fixed rate, fixed term transactions.”<footnote ref="50">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; OTS Letter P-2003-9 (Dec. 2, 2003).</footnote>

            Under the interim final rule, however, such transactions are no longer alternative mortgage transactions. Yet transactions that are specifically mentioned in the second and third prongs of the original AMTPA definition, such as shared-equity/shared-appreciation transactions and renewable balloon-payment transactions (which involve renegotiation of or adjustments to the rate or finance charge), <em data-original="E-03">do</em> continue to be alternative mortgage transactions under the interim final rule. Furthermore, under the interim final rule, a mortgage with <em data-original="E-03">both</em> an adjustable or renegotiable rate or finance charge <em data-original="E-03">and</em> one or more other “nontraditional” features continues to be an “alternative mortgage transaction.” (However, as discussed below with respect to § 1004.3, the scope of AMTPA preemption has also been narrowed such that alternative mortgage transactions with certain nontraditional features like interest-only payments or negative amortization are subject to greater state regulation under the amended statute.)</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>The CFPB recognizes that the amendments to AMTPA's definition could be interpreted differently. Specifically, by eliminating references to balloon payment loans and shared-equity/shared-appreciation mortgages, the amendment could be interpreted as excluding all such transactions from the definition of an alternative mortgage transaction. In addition, the amendment removed a provision that defined alternative mortgage transactions as loans with variations to the rate, method of determining return, term, repayment, or other variations not common to traditional fixed-rate, fixed-term transactions. However, rather than attempting to identify each and every type of loan that could potentially fall under the deleted portions of the definition, the CFPB believes that, for purposes of this interim final rule, the best approach is to focus on whether particular types of transactions fit within the remaining statutory definition.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>As discussed further below, the Dodd-Frank Act's amendments to both the definition of “alternative mortgage transaction” and to the scope of preemption under AMTPA are subject to different interpretations and are interrelated. The CFPB seeks public comment about how best to effectuate congressional intent through implementing regulations that will protect consumers, promote parity, and be readily understandable and applicable by creditors, supervising agencies, and others. The CFPB also requests comment on whether any specific types of mortgages should be excluded from the definition of an alternative mortgage transaction.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph><em data-original="E-03">Mortgages with adjustable rates or finance charges.</em> Comment 2(a)-2 provides specific examples of transactions that are alternative mortgage transactions.<footnote ref="51">These examples are consistent with the definition of an “adjustable rate mortgage loan” in AMTPA, 12 U.S.C. 3806(d)(2), as one in which the loan agreement permits the creditor to adjust the rate of interest from time to time. While the definition of “adjustable rate mortgage loan” applies to a section of AMTPA that requires adjustable rate mortgages to have maximum interest rates (rather than to the preemption provisions), it sheds light on the types of loans contemplated by AMTPA as having adjustable rates.</footnote>
            Examples of alternative mortgage transactions include transactions in which the interest rate changes in accordance with changes to an index and transactions in which the interest rate may be increased or decreased after a specified period of time or under specified circumstances. For example, the definition includes loans in which the interest rate or finance charge may be adjusted after a period of time as specified and defined by the contract, for instance to provide a “timely payment discount rate” upon an anniversary of loan origination to borrowers who have made timely payments for a specified period of time.<footnote ref="52">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; OTS Letter P-2003-9 (Dec. 2, 2003); OTS Letter P-96-13 (Nov. 27, 1996).</footnote>
            (However, as discussed below with respect to § 1004.3, generally applicable state laws governing late charges, including increases in the interest rate due to default, are no longer preempted by AMTPA.)</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>The definition of “alternative mortgage transaction” in § 1004.2(a) includes “variable rate transactions” as defined under Regulation Z for purposes of providing disclosures under 12 CFR 226.19(b).<footnote ref="53">As discussed below, Regulation Z also treats renewable balloon payment loans as variable rate transactions. See 12 CFR 226.17 comment 17(b)-11.</footnote>
            The definition is also similar to the OCC's definition of “adjustable rate mortgage” under its AMTPA regulations.<footnote ref="54">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; 12 CFR 34.20, 34.24 (authorizing state chartered banks to make &amp;#8220;adjustable rate mortgages,&amp;#8221; defined generally to include secured extensions of credit &amp;#8220;where the lender, pursuant to an agreement with the borrower, may adjust the rate of interest from time to time&amp;#8221;).</footnote>
            
          </analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>With regard to shared appreciation and shared equity features in particular, although the Dodd-Frank Act amendments to AMTPA deleted the specific language referencing shared appreciation and shared equity mortgages, loans with these features continue to fall within the remaining definition of “alternative mortgage transaction” because they are mortgage transactions in which a finance charge is adjustable. Indeed, the CFPB notes that Regulation Z currently categorizes shared-equity/shared appreciation mortgages as variable-rate transactions.<footnote ref="55">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; 12 CFR 226 comment 17(c)(1)-11.</footnote>
            Accordingly, consistent with that interpretation, the interim final rule includes such mortgages within the definition of alternative mortgage transaction.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>The CFPB seeks comment on whether the products discussed above should be considered alternative mortgage transactions and what other products in the current market have adjustable rates or finance charges. The CFPB in particular seeks comment on whether treating a mortgage that permits a rate adjustment upon default as an alternative mortgage transaction is an appropriate approach in light of the Dodd-Frank Act amendments that specifically preserve states' authority to regulate late charges.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph><em data-original="E-03">Mortgages with renegotiable rates or finance charges.</em> The statute does not define what types of loans provide for the “renegotiat[ion]” of the interest rate or finance charge. The CFPB does not believe that Congress intended this language to apply to every transaction in which the interest rate or finance charge might theoretically be renegotiated. Such an interpretation could encompass almost any mortgage transaction. Instead, the CFPB believes it is appropriate to consider historical regulations and interpretations issued by the FHLBB and by the Federal Reserve Board under Regulation Z, both of which suggest that “renegotiable rate mortgages” were commonly understood at the time that AMTPA was enacted to include a subset of fixed-rate balloon loans involving renewable short-term notes secured by long-term mortgages, where the creditor made a commitment to renew the notes but reserved discretion to adjust the interest rate at renewal.<footnote ref="56">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See, e.g.&lt;/em&gt;, 45 FR 24,108 (Apr. 9, 1980). The FHLBB initially provided very detailed rules regarding renegotiable rate mortgages, which were subsumed into regulations on adjustable rate mortgages at 46 FR 24,148 (Apr. 30, 1981). The Federal Reserve also has moved from a narrower definition of &amp;#8220;renegotiable rate mortgages&amp;#8221; to a broader category of &amp;#8220;renewable&amp;#8221; balloon loans. &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;Compare&lt;/em&gt; 66 Fed.Res.Bull. 830 (Oct. 1980) (defining &amp;#8220;renegotiable rate mortgages&amp;#8221; to include fixed-rate balloon loan mortgages for which the lender was obliged to renew the loan upon expiration of the loan on the same credit terms except for a change in the interest rate, and interpreting Regulation Z to permit lenders to disclose such mortgages either as a variable-rate obligation under 12 CFR 226.8(b)(8) or as a balloon-payment obligation under 12 CFR 226.8(b)(3)), &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; 56 FR 13751, 13754 (Apr. 4, 1991) (dropping the term &amp;#8220;renegotiable rate mortgage&amp;#8221; in favor of a more generic category of renewable loans with balloon payments, where the creditor is either unconditionally obligated to renew the loan or obligated to renew subject only to conditions within the consumer's control, and requiring that such loans be disclosed as long-term variable rate loans rather than as short-term balloon loans).</footnote>
            
          </analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>This commitment to renew distinguishes renegotiable/renewable loans from a broader and more generic category of balloon loans that was included in AMTPA's original definition of “alternative mortgage transaction,” but was then removed from the definition by the Dodd-Frank Act amendments. That language referred to loans “involving a fixed rate, but which implicitly permit[] rate adjustments by having the debt mature at the end of an interval shorter than the term of the amortization schedule,” without reference or regard to renewal commitments.<footnote ref="57">12 U.S.C. 3802(1)(B).</footnote>
            
          </analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>As discussed above, the fact that Section 1083 deleted the reference to balloon loans while retaining the reference to loans for which the interest rate or finance charge may be renegotiated creates significant ambiguity as to how balloon loans should be treated under AMTPA as amended. However, based on available information, it is unclear to what the phrase “renegotiable rate” in the amended AMTPA definition refers, if not to balloon loans where there is a commitment to renew the loan but the rate is subject to renegotiation.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>For these reasons, the CFPB believes that, for purposes of this interim final rule, it is appropriate to construe the category of renegotiable rate loans to include fixed-rate balloon loans in which the lender has committed to renew the loan. For example, the interim final rule provides that, if a loan has, for instance, a 30-year amortization period but a balloon payment is due at the end of five years, the product is an “alternative mortgage transaction” for purposes of AMTPA if the creditor commits to renew the mortgage.<footnote ref="58">This approach is also consistent with the OCC's regulations applicable to AMTPA loans, which define “adjustable rate mortgages” to exclude “fixed-rate extensions of credit that are payable at the end of a term that, when added to any terms for which the bank has promised to renew the loan, is shorter than the term of the amortization schedule.” 12 CFR 34.20. Thus, if the bank promises to renew the loan for the term of the amortization schedule, the loan fell within the OCC's definition of “adjustable rate mortgage.”</footnote>
            The CFPB notes that the requirement of a lender commitment to renew can help protect borrowers from the heightened default risk associated with balloon payments.<footnote ref="59">See, &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;e.g.,&lt;/em&gt; Roberto G. Quercia, Michael A. Stegman &amp;amp; Walter Davis, &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;The impact of predatory loan terms on subprime foreclosures: The special case of prepayment penalties and balloon payments,&lt;/em&gt; 18 Housing Pol'y Debate 311 (2007) (finding that first-lien subprime refinance mortgage loans with balloon payments in general were 50% more likely to go into foreclosure than other loans, holding other factors constant).</footnote>
            Furthermore, as discussed below with respect to § 1004.4(b), this commitment must be made in writing in order for the transaction to receive AMTPA preemption.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>The CFPB seeks comment on all aspects of this issue, including comment on what products, if any, should be considered renegotiable rate loans, how commitments to renew are typically structured, and whether further clarity or protections may be appropriate for these mortgage products.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph><em data-original="E-03">Adjustable or renegotiable rate loans with additional nontraditional features.</em> As noted above, the interim final rule defines “alternative mortgage transaction” by focusing on the language of the amended statutory definition—in other words, whether the loan has an adjustable or renegotiable rate or finance charge. It is unclear whether the deletion of AMTPA's language recognizing other nontraditional loan features such as negative amortization or interest-only payment periods was intended to exclude adjustable rate or renegotiable rate loans that also contain such features from AMTPA preemption. For purposes of the interim final rule, the CFPB has concluded that such loans should not be excluded, for several reasons.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>First, a broader exclusion based on the absence of statutory text would create a number of practical difficulties. The definitions removed from AMTPA mention two specific loan types—balloon loans and shared-equity/shared-appreciation loans—which can, in certain circumstances, be loans with adjustable or renegotiable rates or finance charges, as discussed above. While this amendment could be interpreted as having been intended to exclude these products from AMTPA coverage entirely, there is no specific language in the amended statute that provides guidance as to why such products would no longer be considered loans with adjustable or renegotiable rates or finance charges, regardless of the other aspects of the loan. In addition, the definitions removed by the Dodd-Frank Act amendments were quite broad and vague and overlap substantially with the other definitions.<footnote ref="60">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; 12 U.S.C. 3802(1)(C) (referring to loans &amp;#8220;involving any &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;similar&lt;/em&gt; type of rate, method of determining return, term, repayment, or other variation not common to traditional fixed rate, fixed term transactions, including without limitation, transactions that involve the sharing of equity or appreciation&amp;#8221;) (emphasis added).</footnote>
            Accordingly, interpreting the amendments to exclude from AMTPA coverage any transactions described in the removed definitions could undermine the remaining definition.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>Second, where unusual circumstances require publication of an interim rule to take immediate effect without advance notice and opportunity for comment, the CFPB believes that it is appropriate to minimize market disruption while the CFPB's notice-and-comment rulemaking is under way. Thus, it is appropriate to interpret the remaining definition of “alternative mortgage transaction” broadly.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>The CFPB also believes it is particularly important to consider the interaction between the Dodd-Frank Act's definitional changes (implemented in § 1004.2) and changes to the scope of preemption (implemented in § 1004.3). Under the definition adopted in the interim final rule, fixed-rate products involving negative amortization, interest-only periods, or graduated payment features do not meet the definition of “alternative mortgage transaction” because they are not loans with adjustable or renegotiable rates or finance charges. Therefore, these types of loans are not eligible for federal preemption under AMTPA and instead are subject to applicable state law.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>In contrast, loans containing the same features that also have adjustable or renegotiable rates or finance charges <em data-original="E-03">would</em> continue to qualify as “alternative mortgage transactions” under the definition in § 1004.2(a). However, state law is preempted with respect to such loans only to the extent provided in § 1004.3 (and only if the transaction also complies with the requirements in § 1004.4(a) through (c), as applicable). Thus, to the extent that a state has enacted a law regulating, for example, negative amortization or interest-only features, AMTPA would not preempt application of that law to an alternative mortgage transaction.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>In addition, although the alternative mortgage transaction <em data-original="E-03">definition</em> includes loans in which the contract permits the creditor to adjust the interest rate or finance charge upon default, applicable state laws governing late charges are not preempted under § 1004.3. Accordingly, like the statute, the two parts of the interim final rule work in conjunction with each other to provide for more consistent application of state law across similar mortgage products.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>The CFPB seeks comment not just about the specific definitional changes but also how those changes relate to the new scope of preemption as further discussed below.</analysisParagraph>
                </analysisSection>
                <analysisSection>
                  <title>(b) Creditor</title>
                  <analysisParagraph>The term “creditor” is defined to have the same meaning as under Regulation Z, 12 CFR 226.2. This reflects the fact that § 1004.4 of the interim final rule applies broadly to all “creditors” as defined under and pursuant to TILA and Regulation Z when such creditors are engaged in the making of alternative mortgage transactions. Comment 2(b)-1 clarifies that, under Regulation Z, the term “creditor” includes federally and state-chartered banks, thrifts, and credit unions, as well as non-depository institutions (such as state-licensed lenders). The comment also references the Official Staff Commentary to Regulation Z for additional guidance on the definition of the term “creditor.”</analysisParagraph>
                </analysisSection>
                <analysisSection>
                  <title>(c) Housing Creditor</title>
                  <analysisParagraph>The definition of “housing creditor” generally mirrors the statutory language to include a depository institution as defined in 12 U.S.C. 1735f-7 note; a lender approved by the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development for participation in any mortgage insurance program under the National Housing Act; other persons who regularly make loans, credit sales, or advances secured by an interest in a residential structure that contains one to four units, whether or not that structure is attached to real property, including an individual condominium unit, cooperative unit, mobile home, and trailer, if it is used as a residence; and any transferee of a person in the other three categories.</analysisParagraph>
                </analysisSection>
                <analysisSection>
                  <title>(d) State</title>
                  <analysisParagraph>The term “State” is defined as a state of the United States, the District of Columbia, and U.S. territories and possessions, including Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, the Northern Mariana Islands, American Samoa, and Guam. This is generally consistent with the federal prudential agencies' regulations as well as the definition of “State” in various other federal consumer financial regulations.<footnote ref="61">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See, e.g.,&lt;/em&gt; 12 CFR 561.50; 12 CFR 563f.2; 12 CFR 700.2.</footnote>
            
          </analysisParagraph>
                </analysisSection>
                <analysisSection>
                  <title>(e) State Law</title>
                  <analysisParagraph>Consistent with 12 U.S.C. 3803, the term “State law” is defined as a State constitution, statute, or regulation or any provision thereof.</analysisParagraph>
                </analysisSection>
              </analysisSection>
            </analysis>
          </section>
          <section label="1004-3" sectionNum="3">
            <subject>§ 1004.3 Preemption of State law.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1004-3-p1" marker="">
              <content>Pursuant to 12 U.S.C. 3803, a State-chartered or -licensed housing creditor may make, purchase, and enforce alternative mortgage transactions in accordance with § 1004.4(a) through (c) of this part (as applicable), notwithstanding any provision of State law that restricts the ability of the housing creditor to adjust or renegotiate an interest rate or finance charge with respect to the transaction or to change the amount of interest or finance charges included in a regular periodic payment as a result of such an adjustment or renegotiation.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <analysis>
              <analysisSection>
                <title>Section 1004.3 Preemption of State law.</title>
                <analysisParagraph>Section 1004.3 provides that a state housing creditor may make, purchase, and enforce alternative mortgage transactions in accordance with the requirements of § 1004.4(a) through (c) (as applicable), notwithstanding any provision of State law that restricts the ability of the housing creditor to adjust or renegotiate an interest rate or finance charge with respect to the transaction or to change the amount of interest or finance charges included in a regular periodic payment as a result of such an adjustment or renegotiation. This regulation generally tracks the language and structure of 12 U.S.C. 3803, as amended by the Dodd-Frank Act. However, in order to implement the purposes of the Dodd-Frank Act's amendments to AMTPA, § 1004.3 interprets and clarifies the amended preemption standard in 12 U.S.C. 3803(c) in several respects.</analysisParagraph>
                <analysisParagraph>As an initial matter, the amendments to 12 U.S.C. 3803(c) narrowed the scope of preemption to apply only to state laws that “ <em data-original="E-03">prohibit</em> [] an alternative mortgage transaction.”<footnote ref="62">Public Law 111-203, § 1083(a)(2)(B) (emphasis added).</footnote>
            Although it is unclear from the statutory text what types of state laws prohibit alternative mortgage transactions for purposes of AMTPA, the amendments to 12 U.S.C. 3803(c) clarify that an alternative mortgage transaction is not prohibited by a state law that “regulates mortgage transactions generally, including any restriction on prepayment penalties or late charges.”<footnote ref="63">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;Id.&lt;/em&gt;</footnote>
            
          </analysisParagraph>
                <analysisParagraph>Neither AMTPA nor the Dodd-Frank Act specifically define the term “prohibit.” However, that term is generally understood to mean forbid by law or to otherwise prevent or hinder an activity.<footnote ref="64">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See, e.g.,&lt;/em&gt; Webster's New World Dictionary 1075 (3d College ed. 1991) (&amp;#8220;1 to refuse to permit; forbid by law or by an order 2 to prevent; hinder&amp;#8221;); Black's Law Dictionary 1331 (9th ed. 2009) (&amp;#8220;Prohibit, vb. 1. To forbid by law. 2. To prevent or hinder.&amp;#8221;).</footnote>
            Furthermore, the purpose of AMTPA remains providing state housing creditors “with parity with federally chartered institutions by authorizing all housing creditors to make, purchase, and enforce alternative mortgage transactions so long as the transactions are in conformity with [federal] regulations. * * * ”<footnote ref="65">12 U.S.C. 3801(b).</footnote>
            This purpose would be thwarted if AMTPA were interpreted not to preempt state laws imposing restrictions on state housing creditors' ability to adjust interest rates and finance charges where such restrictions do not apply to federal housing creditors, as the ability to make such adjustments is integral to alternative mortgage transactions. Accordingly, because 12 U.S.C. 3802(1) defines an alternative mortgage transaction as a transaction “in which the interest rate or finance charge may be adjusted or renegotiated,” the interim final rule construes “prohibit” to include not only state laws banning the making, purchase, or enforcement of alternative mortgage transactions, but also state laws that restrict or hinder the adjustment or renegotiation of an interest rate or finance charge. For example, as explained in comment 2, state laws are preempted to the extent that they restrict the circumstances under which a rate may be adjusted, the method by which a rate may be adjusted, or the amount of a rate adjustment.</analysisParagraph>
                <analysisParagraph>Similarly, § 1004.3 provides that state laws are preempted with respect to alternative mortgage transactions to the extent that they restrict the ability of a state housing creditor to change the amount of a payment to include increased interest or finance charges as a result of the adjustment or renegotiation of an interest rate or finance charge. The CFPB believes that such changes to payment amounts are also integral to alternative mortgage transactions. Indeed, if housing creditors were not permitted to increase the payment amount to account for an increase in the interest rate, the transaction could negatively amortize, which would be harmful to some consumers.<footnote ref="66">However, as explained in comment 2, other state law restrictions on changes to payments are not preempted by § 1004.3.</footnote>
            
          </analysisParagraph>
                <analysisParagraph>Comment 1 clarifies that, regardless of whether a state law applies solely to alternative mortgage transactions or applies to both alternative mortgage transactions and other mortgage or consumer credit transactions, that law is preempted by § 1004.3 to the extent that it restricts the ability of a state housing creditor to adjust or renegotiate an interest rate or finance charge with respect to an alternative mortgage transaction or to adjust payments as a result of such an adjustment or renegotiation. Thus, the preemption regime under § 1004.3 is not tied to whether a state law by its terms applies solely to alternative mortgage transactions.</analysisParagraph>
                <analysisParagraph>Although the amendments to 12 U.S.C. 3803(c) indicate that state laws that regulate mortgage transactions generally are not preempted, the CFPB believes that narrowly focusing on whether a state law is by its terms general or specific would undermine the key determination of whether a state law <em data-original="E-03">prohibits</em> an alternative mortgage transaction's adjustment or renegotiation of an interest rate or finance charge or changes to payments as a result of the adjustment or renegotiation. For example, applying preemption to any state law that specifically addresses alternative mortgage transactions would preempt state laws that do not prohibit alternative mortgage transactions because they do not forbid, prevent, or hinder the ability of the state housing creditor to make such transactions (such as a state law requiring that certain disclosures be provided regarding alternative mortgage transactions). Furthermore, this approach would shield from preemption state laws that might be couched in general terms but effectively prohibit an alternative mortgage transaction (for example, a law prohibiting increases in an interest rate based on increases in an index). Finally, focusing solely on whether a state law is specific to alternative mortgage transactions or more general in its terms could lead to anomalous results if, for example, one state prohibited certain conduct in a statute that specifically applied to alternative mortgage transactions while another state prohibited the same conduct in a statute that applied generally to all mortgage transactions. For these reasons, the CFPB believes that it would be inconsistent with the goals of the Dodd-Frank Act amendments to make AMTPA preemption determinations based solely on whether a state law was specific or general by its terms.</analysisParagraph>
                <analysisParagraph>Comment 2 also clarifies that state law restrictions on shared equity or shared appreciation transactions in which the creditor and the consumer share some or all of the appreciation in the value of the property are preempted by § 1004.3. As discussed above, such transactions are alternative mortgage transactions under § 1004.2(a). However, the CFPB solicits comment on whether additional protections are needed with respect to these types of transactions. The CFPB also solicits comment on the volume of these transactions.</analysisParagraph>
                <analysisParagraph>In addition, comment 2 clarifies that state law underwriting requirements are preempted by § 1004.3 to the extent that they effectively restrict the adjustment or renegotiation of interest rates or finance charges or changes in payments as a result of such adjustments or renegotiations. For example, if a state law requires housing creditors to underwrite based on the maximum contractual rate, that particular provision of the law is preempted by § 1004.3 with respect to alternative mortgage transactions, regardless of whether the provision applies solely to alternative mortgage transactions or to both alternative mortgage transactions and other mortgage or consumer credit transactions. In contrast, state underwriting requirements of general applicability that do not impact the adjustment or renegotiation of interest rates or finance charges or changes in payments as a result of such adjustments or renegotiations are not preempted. (However, as discussed below, § 1004.4(c) requires state housing creditors that invoke AMTPA preemption to comply Regulation Z's underwriting requirements for high-cost and higher-cost mortgages.)</analysisParagraph>
                <analysisParagraph>In contrast, comment 3 provides examples of state laws that are not preempted by § 1004.3 because they do not restrict the ability of the housing creditor to adjust or renegotiate an interest rate or finance charge or to change the amount of a payment as a result of such an adjustment or renegotiation. In particular, the comment states that, consistent with the amended 12 U.S.C. 3803(c), state law restrictions on prepayment penalties and late charges are not preempted by § 1004.3 regardless of whether the restriction applies solely to alternative mortgage transactions or to both alternative mortgage transactions and other mortgage or consumer credit transactions. Such a restriction does not prohibit or hinder a feature integral to an alternative mortgage transaction. The comment further clarifies that an increase in an interest rate or finance charge as a result of a late payment is a late charge for purposes of § 1004.3. Therefore, a state law that prohibits state housing creditors from increasing a consumer's interest rate as a result of a late payment is not preempted by § 1004.3.</analysisParagraph>
                <analysisParagraph>In addition, comment 3 clarifies that state law restrictions on transactions in which one or more of the regular periodic payments may result in an increase in the principal balance (a negative amortization feature) or may be applied solely to accrued interest and not to loan principal (an interest-only feature) are not preempted by § 1004.3. The comment also clarifies that state law disclosure requirements are not preempted by § 1004.3 regardless of whether the law applies specifically to alternative mortgage transactions because disclosure requirements do not prohibit a state housing creditor from adjusting or renegotiating an interest rate or finance charge or making a corresponding change to a payment. Finally, the CFPB notes that, as a general matter, state laws prohibiting unfair or deceptive acts or practices are not preempted under 12 U.S.C. 3803(c) or this interim final rule.</analysisParagraph>
                <analysisParagraph>The CFPB seeks comment on all aspects of § 1004.3(b) and on whether particular state laws should or should not be subject to AMTPA preemption. The CFPB notes, however, that nothing in this interim final rule affects the preemption of state law under provisions of federal law other than AMTPA.</analysisParagraph>
              </analysisSection>
            </analysis>
          </section>
          <section label="1004-4" sectionNum="4">
            <subject>§ 1004.4 Requirements for alternative mortgage transactions.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1004-4-a" marker="(a)">
              <title type="keyterm">Mortgages with adjustable rates or finance charges and home equity lines of credit.</title>
              <content>Mortgages with adjustable rates or finance charges and home equity lines of credit. A creditor that makes an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> with an adjustable rate or finance charge may only increase the interest rate or finance charge as follows:</content>
              <paragraph label="1004-4-a-1" marker="(1)">
                <content>If the transaction is subject to <ref target="CFR:12-226-5" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.5</ref>b, the creditor must comply with <ref target="CFR:12-226-5" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.5</ref>b(f)(1).</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-4-a-2" marker="(2)">
                <content>For all other transactions, the creditor must use either:</content>
                <paragraph label="1004-4-a-2-i" marker="(i)">
                  <content>An index to which changes in the interest rate are tied that is readily available to and verifiable by the borrower and beyond the control of the creditor; or</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph label="1004-4-a-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
                  <content>A formula or schedule identifying the amount that the interest rate or finance charge may increase and the times at which, or circumstances under which, a change may be made.</content>
                </paragraph>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-4-b" marker="(b)">
              <title type="keyterm">Renegotiable rates for renewable balloon-payment mortgages.</title>
              <content>Renegotiable rates for renewable balloon-payment mortgages. A creditor that makes an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> with payments based on an amortization period and a large final payment due after a shorter term may negotiate an increase or decrease in the interest rate when the transaction is renewed only if the creditor makes a written commitment to renew the transaction at specified intervals throughout the amortization period. However, the creditor is not required to renew the transaction if:</content>
              <paragraph label="1004-4-b-1" marker="(1)">
                <content>Any action or inaction by the consumer materially and adversely affects the creditor's security for the transaction or any right of the creditor in such security;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-4-b-2" marker="(2)">
                <content>There is a material failure by the consumer to meet the repayment terms of the transaction;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-4-b-3" marker="(3)">
                <content>There is fraud or a willful or knowing material misrepresentation by the consumer in connection with the transaction; or</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-4-b-4" marker="(4)">
                <content>Federal law dealing with credit extended by a depository institution to its executive officers specifically requires that as a condition of the extension the credit shall become due and payable on demand, provided that the creditor includes such a provision in the initial agreement.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-4-c" marker="(c)">
              <title type="keyterm">Requirements for high-cost and higher-priced mortgage loans.</title>
              <content>Requirements for high-cost and higher-priced mortgage loans.</content>
              <paragraph label="1004-4-c-1" marker="(1)">
                <content>If an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> is subject to <ref target="CFR:12-226-32" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.32</ref>, the creditor must comply with <ref target="CFR:12-226-32" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.32</ref> and <ref target="CFR:12-226-34" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.34</ref>.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-4-c-2" marker="(2)">
                <content>If an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> is subject to <ref target="CFR:12-226-35" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.35</ref>, the creditor must comply with <ref target="CFR:12-226-35" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.35</ref>.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-4-d" marker="(d)">
              <title type="keyterm">Other applicable law.</title>
              <content>Other applicable law. Notwithstanding paragraphs <ref target="1004-4-a" reftype="internal">(a)</ref> through <ref target="1004-4-c" reftype="internal">(c)</ref> of this section, a <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditor</ref> that is not making an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> pursuant to § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref> of this part may make that transaction consistent with applicable <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">State</ref> or Federal law other than this section.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-4-e" marker="(e)">
              <title type="keyterm">Reductions in interest rate or finance charge.</title>
              <content>Reductions in interest rate or finance charge. Nothing in this section prohibits a creditor from decreasing the interest rate or finance charge on an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref>.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <analysis>
              <analysisSection>
                <title>Section 1004.4 Requirements for Alternative Mortgage Transactions</title>
                <analysisParagraph>Section 1083 of the Dodd-Frank Act requires the CFPB to promulgate its own regulations governing alternative mortgage transactions after the designated transfer date. The CFPB is also required to review and determine whether the regulations governing alternative mortgage transactions designated by the OCC and NCUA pursuant to AMTPA are “fair, not deceptive, and consistent with the purposes of [title X of the Dodd-Frank Act].”<footnote ref="67">Public Law 111-203, § 1083(b).</footnote>

            The CFPB believes that it is consistent with the intent and purpose of Section 1083 to interpret this provision as requiring the CFPB to determine whether the OCC and NCUA regulations are effective in <em data-original="E-03">preventing</em> unfair or deceptive practices. In addition, although this provision does not require the CFPB to review OTS AMTPA regulations, the CFPB believes that it is appropriate to do so in order to predict potential impacts on the marketplace.</analysisParagraph>
                <analysisParagraph>Accordingly, the CFPB has completed an initial review of the regulations designated by the OCC, NCUA, and OTS as well as agency interpretive guidance, available court decisions, and secondary sources. Based on this review, the CFPB has made a preliminary determination that certain of those regulations are necessary to prevent unfairness and deception and are consistent with the purposes of title X of the Dodd-Frank Act. The CFPB has adopted those regulations in modified form in § 1004.4(a) and (b) of the interim final rule. However, the CFPB believes that additional research, consultation, and comment are needed before adoption of a permanent final rule. The CFPB therefore seeks comment on whether the requirements in § 1004.4 are sufficient to prevent unfair or deceptive acts or practices, whether modifications to those requirements are appropriate, and whether additional protections are needed.</analysisParagraph>
                <analysisParagraph>As discussed above, the CFPB is issuing § 1004.4 pursuant to its authority under TILA, which applies to all “creditors” as defined by Regulation Z. Thus, § 1004.4 applies to all federal and state housing creditors that make alternative mortgage transactions. However, because there has not yet been an opportunity for notice and comment on the requirements in § 1004.4(a) through (c), the CFPB has delayed mandatory compliance with § 1004.4 until July 21, 2012 for federal housing creditors and for state housing creditors that are not relying on preemption of state law under § 1004.3. Accordingly, only state housing creditors that choose to seek AMTPA preemption under § 1004.3 are required to comply with § 1004.4 before July 22, 2012.<footnote ref="68">As discussed below, however, nothing in Part 1004 alters the obligation of all creditors to continue to comply with the requirements of Regulation Z that are incorporated by reference in § 1004.4 (specifically, 12 CFR 226.5b, 12 CFR 226.32, 12 CFR 226.34, and 12 CFR 226.35, as applicable).</footnote>
            
          </analysisParagraph>
                <analysisParagraph>The CFPB's interim final rule is designed to protect consumers and preserve access to credit and federal-state parity while also providing an orderly transition period while the notice-and-comment rulemaking process occurs. Because the OCC, NCUA, and OTS AMTPA rules vary significantly in substance and scope and because the CFPB's rules must account for the Dodd-Frank Act amendments to AMTPA, the CFPB has concluded that it would not be practicable or appropriate to simply replicate the three pre-existing sets of regulations in the CFPB's interim final rule. However, the CFPB has adopted standards and language that are comparable to central elements of those regulations where it was consistent with the Dodd-Frank Act and otherwise appropriate to do so.</analysisParagraph>
                <analysisParagraph>The CFPB did consider simply requiring state housing creditors to comply with all requirements of federal law in order to receive AMTPA preemption. However, because state housing creditors are already required to comply with TILA and other applicable provisions of federal law that fall within the CFPB's authority, such an approach would be redundant and unnecessary and could cause confusion regarding the scope of preemption under § 1004.3. Instead, as discussed below, that CFPB has designated specific provisions of Regulation Z in § 1004.4.</analysisParagraph>
                <analysisParagraph>The CFPB notes that AMTPA provides an opportunity to cure violations of federal alternative mortgage transaction regulations that may be helpful to state housing creditors as they make adjustments necessary to comply with the interim final rule. Specifically, 12 U.S.C. 3803(b) provides that, where a state housing creditor has failed to comply with the alternative mortgage transaction regulations for federally chartered housing creditors, an alternative mortgage transaction will nonetheless be deemed to be made in accordance with the applicable regulation if: “(1) The transaction is in substantial compliance with the regulation; and (2) within sixty days of discovering any error the housing creditor corrects such error, including making appropriate adjustments, if any, to the account.”</analysisParagraph>
                <analysisSection>
                  <title>(a) Adjustable rate mortgages.</title>
                  <analysisParagraph>Section 1004.4(a) of the interim final rule provides standards by which creditors making alternative mortgage transactions with adjustable rates or finance charges may increase the interest rate or finance charge. To rely on AMTPA's preemption provision, creditors making alternative mortgage transactions that are open-end home equity lines of credit subject to the Regulation Z requirements in 12 CFR 226.5b must comply with § 226.5b's requirement that changes in the annual percentage rate be made according to a publicly available index that is not subject to the creditor's control.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>For closed-end alternative mortgage transactions involving an adjustable rate or finance charge, the interim final rule provides that adjustments must be made based on either: (1) an index outside the creditor's control to which changes in the interest rate are tied; or (2) a formula or schedule identifying the amount by which the interest rate or finance charge may increase and the times at which, or circumstances under which, a change may be made. The content of these rules is similar to the OCC and OTS regulations for national banks and federal thrifts, respectively, that were previously designated as applicable to state housing creditors under AMTPA.<footnote ref="69">12 CFR 34.20-25; 12 CFR 560.220.</footnote>
            Pursuant to its authority under Section 1405(a) of the Dodd-Frank Act (15 U.S.C. 1639b(e)(1)), the CFPB finds that the adoption of the standards in § 1004.4(a) as part of this interim final rule is necessary and proper to ensure that responsible, affordable mortgage credit remains available to consumers. Nevertheless, the CFPB seeks comment on whether additional or different requirements are more appropriate to protect consumers and promote parity between federal and state housing creditors.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>Comment 4(a)-1 clarifies that a creditor may use any measure of index values that meets the requirements in § 1004.4(a)(2)(i). For example, the index may be either single values as of a specific date or an average of values calculated over a specified period.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>Comment 4(a)-2 clarifies that an index is not beyond the creditor's control if the index is the creditor's own prime rate or cost of funds. A creditor is permitted to use a published prime rate, such as the prime rate published in the <em data-original="E-03">Wall Street Journal.</em>
            <footnote ref="70">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; 12 CFR 226.5b comment 5b(f)(1)-1.</footnote>
            The CFPB notes that, in other contexts, the Federal Reserve Board has concluded that a creditor's use of “rate floors” (in other words, minimum values below which the interest rate will not fall regardless of the index value) constituted control over the operation of an index.<footnote ref="71">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; 12 CFR 226.55(b)(2) comment 55(b)(2)-2.</footnote>
            Although the CFPB has not adopted that interpretation in this interim final rule, it seeks comment on whether it is appropriate to do so in a permanent final regulation implementing the amendments to AMTPA.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>Comment 4(a)-3 clarifies that a publicly available index need not be published in a newspaper, but it must be one the consumer can independently obtain (by telephone, for example) and use to verify the annual percentage rate applied to the alternative mortgage transaction.<footnote ref="72">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; 12 CFR 226.5b comment 5b(f)(1)-2</footnote>
            
          </analysisParagraph>
                </analysisSection>
                <analysisSection>
                  <title>(b) Renegotiable rates for balloon-payment mortgages.</title>
                  <analysisParagraph>Renegotiable rates and renewable balloon-payment mortgages were not specifically discussed in the mortgage rules previously designated as applicable to state housing creditors under AMTPA by the OCC, NCUA, and OTS. However, pursuant to its authority under Section 1405(a) of the Dodd-Frank Act (15 U.S.C. 1639b(e)(1)), the CFPB finds that adoption of the standards in § 1004.4(b) as part of this interim final rule is necessary and proper to ensure that responsible, affordable mortgage credit remains available to consumers.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>As discussed above, a renewable balloon-payment mortgage is generally a transaction in which payments are based on an amortization period and a large final payment is due after a shorter term, but the borrower has the option to renew the transaction at specified intervals throughout the amortization period at the interest rate offered by the creditor at the time of renewal.<footnote ref="73">See 12 CFR 226.17 comment 17(b)-11.</footnote>
            To rely on AMTPA's preemption provision, creditors making such transactions must provide a written commitment to renew the transaction at specified intervals throughout the amortization period. Under the terms of the written commitment, the creditor may negotiate an increase or decrease in the interest rate at renewal.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>The CFPB believes that a written commitment is necessary to ensure that balloon-payment mortgages made under AMTPA are provided responsibly. However, the CFPB also believes that, based on safety and soundness and other considerations, creditors should not be required to renew the loan in certain limited circumstances. Accordingly, the CFPB has adopted exceptions to the renewal requirement based on the exceptions in 12 CFR 226.5b(f)(2), which permit a creditor to terminate a home-equity line of credit and demand payment of the outstanding balance. The CFPB has modified the § 226.5b(f)(2) exceptions to ensure that a creditor generally cannot decline to renew a balloon-payment loan under § 1004.4(b) unless there has been a material change in circumstance.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>Therefore, § 1004.4(b) provides that the creditor is not required to renew the transaction if: (1) Any action or inaction by the consumer materially and adversely affects the creditor's security for the transaction or any right of the creditor in such security; (2) there is a material failure by the consumer to meet the repayment terms of the transaction; (3) there is fraud or a willful or knowing material misrepresentation by the consumer in connection with the transaction; or (4) Federal law dealing with credit extended by a depository institution to its executive officers specifically requires that as a condition of the extension the credit shall become due and payable on demand, provided that the creditor includes such a provision in the initial agreement.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>The CFPB seeks comment on whether the written commitment requirement and the exceptions in § 1004.4(b) are appropriate to protect consumers, promote access to responsible credit, and enhance parity between federal and state housing creditors.</analysisParagraph>
                </analysisSection>
                <analysisSection>
                  <title>(c) Requirements for High-Cost and Higher-Priced Mortgage Loans</title>
                  <analysisParagraph>Section 1004.4(c) provides that, if an alternative mortgage transaction is a “high-cost” loan subject to 12 CFR 226.32, the creditor must comply with 12 CFR 226.32 and 12 CFR 226.34. In addition, if an alternative mortgage transaction is a “higher-priced mortgage loan” subject to 12 CFR 226.35, the creditor must comply with 12 CFR 226.35. These provisions of Regulation Z contain underwriting requirements and restrictions on loan terms for certain types of loans with higher costs. Because the interim final rule preempts some state underwriting requirements, the CFPB believes it is appropriate to require creditors to comply with these provisions in order to obtain that preemption.<footnote ref="74">Because 12 CFR 226.32, 12 CFR 226.34, and 12 CFR 226.35 already apply to all creditors, all creditors must continue to comply with those provisions, regardless of whether they seek AMTPA preemption.</footnote>
            Pursuant to its authority under Section 1405(a) of the Dodd-Frank Act (15 U.S.C. 1639b(e)(1)), the CFPB finds that the adoption of § 1004.4(c) as part of this interim final rule is necessary and proper to ensure that responsible, affordable mortgage credit remains available to consumers.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>Comment 1004.3(c)-1 clarifies that creditors must comply with the restrictions on prepayment penalties in Regulation Z, if applicable. However, as discussed above, creditors are <em data-original="E-03">not</em> exempt under AMTPA and § 1004.3 from state laws regarding prepayment penalties. Thus, with respect to prepayment penalties, creditors must comply with both Regulation Z and with state law unless another basis for preemption exists (such as because the state law is inconsistent with Regulation Z).<footnote ref="75">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; 12 CFR 226.28.</footnote>
            For example, if a loan is a higher-priced mortgage loan under 12 CFR 226.35, it may not have a prepayment penalty unless the penalty expires within two years after consummation.<footnote ref="76">12 CFR 226.35(b)(2)(ii)(A).</footnote>
            However, if a state law prohibited prepayment penalties unless the penalty expires within one year, that state law would not be preempted by AMTPA (or by Regulation Z).</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>The CFPB seeks comment on the inclusion of these requirements in § 1004.4(c) and on whether additional underwriting requirements are warranted. In particular, the CFPB requests comment on whether, once the regulations implementing the ability-to-pay requirements in TILA Section 129C (15 U.S.C. 1639c) are finalized, all or part of those regulations should be incorporated into § 1004.4(c).</analysisParagraph>
                </analysisSection>
                <analysisSection>
                  <title>(d) Other Applicable Law</title>
                  <analysisParagraph>Because § 1004.4 applies to all creditors on July 22, 2012, the interim final rule provides § 1004.4(d) as an alternative to compliance with § 1004.4(a) through (c) for creditors that do not seek preemption under § 1004.3. Specifically, § 1004.4(d) permits a housing creditor that is not making an alternative mortgage transaction pursuant to § 1004.3 to make that transaction consistent with applicable state or federal law other than § 1004.4. Thus, for example, a state housing creditor that does not invoke AMTPA preemption can make an alternative mortgage transaction consistent with applicable state law as well as applicable federal law other than § 1004.4. Similarly, a federally chartered housing creditor can make an alternative mortgage transaction consistent with federal law other than § 1004.4 (including any requirements imposed by the chartering agency and the requirements for high-cost and higher-priced mortgage loans found in 12 CFR 226.32, 12 CFR 226.34, and 12 CFR 226.35) as well as any applicable state law.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>Particularly in view of the fact that this interim final rule is being published without notice and comment, the CFPB believes that this provision is necessary and appropriate to enable housing creditors that are not using AMTPA preemption to make alternative mortgage transactions to continue making such transactions in accordance with applicable federal or state standards. The CFPB believes that this interim final rule strikes an appropriate short-term balance that will promote greater parity between federal and state housing creditors, continued access to credit on currently-available terms, and consumer protection while reflecting the narrowed scope of AMTPA preemption under the Dodd-Frank Act. The CFPB seeks comment on both the short-term impacts of this provision and on potential long-term standards under § 1004.4 that would apply to all creditors or a defined subset of creditors. In addition, the CFPB seeks comment on whether it should utilize sources of statutory authority other than TILA to issue regulations governing alternative mortgage transactions.</analysisParagraph>
                  <analysisParagraph>Comment 4(d)-1 clarifies that § 1004.4(d) does not exempt housing creditors that do not seek preemption under § 1004.3 from complying with provisions of federal law that are incorporated by reference in § 1004.4. Specifically, nothing in § 1004.4(d) exempts a housing creditor from complying with 12 CFR 226.5b, 226.32, 226.34, or 226.35.</analysisParagraph>
                </analysisSection>
                <analysisSection>
                  <title>(e) Reductions in interest rate or finance charge.</title>
                  <analysisParagraph>Section 1004.4(e) of the interim final rule provides that a creditor may always decrease the interest rate or finance charge on an alternative mortgage transaction without violating § 1004.4. The OCC regulations that are designated as applicable to state housing creditors contain a similar provision, and the CFPB believes it is appropriate to replicate that provision here because interest rate and finance charge reductions are beneficial to consumers.</analysisParagraph>
                </analysisSection>
              </analysisSection>
            </analysis>
          </section>
        </content>
      </subpart>
      <appendix appendixLetter="A" label="1004-A">
        <appendixTitle>Appendix A to Part 1004—Official Commentary on Regulation D</appendixTitle>
        <tableOfContents>
          <tocAppEntry target="1004-A-h1">
            <appendixLetter>h1</appendixLetter>
            <appendixSubject>§ 1004.1 Authority, Purpose, and Scope</appendixSubject>
          </tocAppEntry>
          <tocAppEntry target="1004-A-h3">
            <appendixLetter>h3</appendixLetter>
            <appendixSubject>§ 1004.2 Definitions</appendixSubject>
          </tocAppEntry>
          <tocAppEntry target="1004-A-h6">
            <appendixLetter>h6</appendixLetter>
            <appendixSubject>§ 1004.3 Preemption of State Law</appendixSubject>
          </tocAppEntry>
          <tocAppEntry target="1004-A-h7">
            <appendixLetter>h7</appendixLetter>
            <appendixSubject>§ 1004.4 Requirements for Alternative Mortgage Transactions</appendixSubject>
          </tocAppEntry>
        </tableOfContents>
        <appendixSection appendixSecNum="1" label="1004-A-h1">
          <subject>§ 1004.1 Authority, Purpose, and Scope</subject>
          <paragraph label="1004-A-h1-h2" marker="">
            <title>1(c) Scope.</title>
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h1-h2-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Application received before July 22, 2011.</title>
              <content>Application received before July 22, 2011. This Part does not apply to a transaction if the creditor received the application for that transaction before July 22, 2011, even if the transaction was consummated or completed on or after July 22, 2011. Whether <ref target="USC:12-3803" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 3803</ref>(c) preempts <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State law</ref> with respect to such a transaction depends on whether: (1) The transaction was an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> as defined by the version of <ref target="USC:12-3802" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 3802</ref>(1) in effect at the time of application; and (2) the <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">State</ref> <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditor</ref> complied with applicable federal regulations issued by the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency, the National Credit Union Administration, the Office of Thrift Supervision, or the Federal Home Loan Bank Board in effect at the time of application.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h1-h2-2" marker="2.">
              <title type="keyterm">Subsequent modifications and other actions.</title>
              <content>Subsequent modifications and other actions. If applicable regulations under <ref target="USC:12-3803" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 3803</ref>(c) (including this Part) preempted <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State law</ref> with respect to an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> at the time the application was received, the following actions with respect to that transaction are entitled to the same degree of preemption under such regulations:</content>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h1-h2-2-i" marker="i.">
                <content>The subsequent consummation, completion, purchase, or enforcement of the transaction by a <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditor</ref>.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h1-h2-2-ii" marker="ii.">
                <content>The subsequent modification, renewal, or extension of the transaction. However, if such a transaction is satisfied and replaced by another transaction, the second transaction must independently meet the requirements for preemption in effect at the time the application for the second transaction was received.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </appendixSection>
        <appendixSection appendixSecNum="2" label="1004-A-h3">
          <subject>§ 1004.2 Definitions</subject>
          <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4" marker="">
            <title>2(a) Alternative Mortgage Transaction</title>
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Alternative mortgage transaction.</title>
              <content><ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">Alternative mortgage transaction</ref>. For purposes of this Part, an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> that meets the definition in § <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="internal">1004.2(a)</ref> includes any consumer credit transaction that is secured by a mortgage, deed of trust, or other equivalent consensual security interest in a dwelling or in residential real property that includes a dwelling. The dwelling need not be the primary dwelling of the consumer. Home equity lines of credit and subordinate lien mortgages are <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> for purposes of this Part to the extent they meet the definition in § <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="internal">1004.2(a)</ref>.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-2" marker="2.">
              <title type="keyterm">Examples of alternative mortgage transactions.</title>
              <content>Examples of <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref>. Examples of <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> include:</content>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-2-i" marker="i.">
                <content>Transactions in which the interest rate changes in accordance with fluctuations in an index.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-2-ii" marker="ii.">
                <content>Transactions in which the interest rate or finance charge may be increased or decreased after a specified period of time or under specified circumstances.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-2-iii" marker="iii.">
                <content>Balloon transactions in which payments are based on an amortization schedule and a large final payment is due after a shorter term, where the creditor makes a commitment to renew the transaction at specified intervals throughout the amortization period, but the interest rate may be renegotiated at renewal. For example, a fixed-rate mortgage loan with a 30-year amortization period but a balloon payment due five years after consummation is an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> under § <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="internal">1004.2(a)</ref> if the creditor commits to renew the mortgage at five-year intervals for the entire 30-year amortization period.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-2-iv" marker="iv.">
                <content>Transactions in which the creditor and the consumer agree to share some or all of the appreciation in the value of the property (shared equity/shared appreciation).</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-2-p1" marker="">
                <content>However, this Part preempts <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State law</ref> only to the extent provided in § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref> and only to the extent that the requirements of § <ref target="1004-4-a" reftype="internal">1004.4(a)</ref> through <ref target="1004-4-c" reftype="internal">(c)</ref> (as applicable) are met.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-3" marker="3.">
              <title type="keyterm">Examples of transactions that are not alternative mortgage transactions.</title>
              <content>Examples of transactions that are not <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref>. The following are examples of transactions that are not <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref>:</content>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-3-i" marker="i.">
                <content>Transactions with a fixed interest rate where one or more of the regular periodic payments may be applied solely to accrued interest and not to loan principal (an interest-only feature).</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-3-ii" marker="ii.">
                <content>Balloon transactions with a fixed interest rate where payments are based on an amortization schedule and a large final payment is due after a shorter term, where the creditor does not make a commitment to renew the transaction at specified intervals throughout the amortization period.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-3-iii" marker="iii.">
                <content>Transactions with a fixed interest rate where one or more of the regular periodic payments may result in an increase in the principal balance (a negative amortization feature).</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h5" marker="">
            <title>2(b) Creditor</title>
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h5-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Creditor.</title>
              <content>Creditor. As defined in <ref target="CFR:12-226-2" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.2</ref>, “creditor” includes federally and <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">State</ref>-chartered banks, thrifts, and credit unions, as well as non-depository institutions, such as <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">State</ref>-licensed lenders. The Official Staff Commentary to <ref target="CFR:12-226-2" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.2</ref> contains additional guidance on the definition of the term “creditor.” See <ref target="CFR:12-226-2" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.2</ref>, Supp. I.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </appendixSection>
        <appendixSection appendixSecNum="3" label="1004-A-h6">
          <subject>§ 1004.3 Preemption of State Law</subject>
          <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-1" marker="1.">
            <title type="keyterm">Scope of State laws.</title>
            <content>Scope of <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State laws</ref>. Regardless of whether a <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State law</ref> applies solely to <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> or applies to both <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> and other mortgage or consumer credit transactions, that law is preempted by § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref> only to the extent that it restricts the ability of a <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">State</ref>-chartered or -licensed <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditor</ref> to adjust or renegotiate an interest rate or finance charge with respect to an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> or to change the amount of interest or finance charges included in a regular periodic payment as a result of such an adjustment or renegotiation.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-2" marker="2.">
            <title type="keyterm">Examples of State laws that are preempted.</title>
            <content>Examples of <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State laws</ref> that are preempted. The following are examples of <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State laws</ref> that are preempted by § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref>:</content>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-2-i" marker="i.">
              <content>Restrictions on the adjustment or renegotiation of an interest rate or finance charge, including restrictions on the circumstances under which a rate or charge may be adjusted, the method by which a rate or charge may be adjusted, and the amount of the adjustment to the rate or charge. For example, if a provision of <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State law</ref> prohibits creditors from increasing an adjustable rate more than two percentage points or from increasing an adjustable rate more than once during a year, that provision is preempted by § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref> with respect to <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> that comply with § <ref target="1004-4-a" reftype="internal">1004.4(a)</ref> through <ref target="1004-4-c" reftype="internal">(c)</ref>, as applicable. Similarly, if a provision of <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State law</ref> prohibits <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditors</ref> from renewing balloon transactions that meet the definition of an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> in § <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="internal">1004.2(a)</ref> on different terms, that provision is preempted by § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref> only to the extent that it restricts a <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">state</ref> <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditor</ref>'s ability to adjust or renegotiate the interest rate or finance charge at renewal. See also comment 1004.3-3.i.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-2-ii" marker="ii.">
              <content>Restrictions on the ability of a <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditor</ref> to change the amount of interest or finance charges included in regular periodic payments as a result of the adjustment or renegotiation of an interest rate or finance charge. For example, if a provision of <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State law</ref> prohibits <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditors</ref> from increasing payments or limits the amount of such increases with respect to both <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> and other mortgage or consumer credit transactions, that provision is preempted by § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref> to the extent that it restricts a <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditor</ref>'s ability to adjust payments as a result of the adjustment or renegotiation of an interest rate on an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref>. Other restrictions on changes to payments are not preempted, including restrictions on transactions in which one or more of the regular periodic payments may result in an increase in the principal balance (a negative amortization feature) or may be applied solely to accrued interest and not to loan principal (an interest-only feature).</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-2-iii" marker="iii.">
              <content>Restrictions on the creditor and the consumer sharing some or all of the appreciation in the value of the property (shared equity/shared appreciation).</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-2-iv" marker="iv.">
              <content>Underwriting requirements that address the adjustment or renegotiation of interest rates or finance charges. For example, if a provision of <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State law</ref> requires <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditors</ref> to underwrite based on the maximum contractual rate, that provision is preempted by § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref> with respect to <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref>, regardless of whether the provision applies solely to <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> or to both <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> and other mortgage or consumer credit transactions.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-3" marker="3.">
            <title type="keyterm">Examples of State laws that are not preempted.</title>
            <content>Examples of <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State laws</ref> that are not preempted. The following are examples of <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State laws</ref> that are not preempted by § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref> regardless of whether the provision applies solely to <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> or to both <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> and other mortgage or consumer credit transactions:</content>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-3-i" marker="i.">
              <content>Restrictions on prepayment penalties or late charges (including an increase in an interest rate or finance charge as a result of a late payment).</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-3-ii" marker="ii.">
              <content>Restrictions on transactions in which one or more of the regular periodic payments may result in an increase in the principal balance (a negative amortization feature) or may be applied solely to accrued interest and not to loan principal (an interest-only feature).</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-3-iii" marker="iii.">
              <content>Requirements that disclosures be provided.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </appendixSection>
        <appendixSection appendixSecNum="4" label="1004-A-h7">
          <subject>§ 1004.4 Requirements for Alternative Mortgage Transactions</subject>
          <paragraph label="1004-A-h7-h8" marker="">
            <title>4(a) Mortgages With Adjustable or Renegotiable Rates or Finance Charges and Home Equity Lines of Credit</title>
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h7-h8-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Index values.</title>
              <content>Index values. A creditor may use any measure of index values that meets the requirements in § <ref target="1004-4-a-2-i" reftype="internal">1004.4(a)(2)(i)</ref>. For example, the index may be either single values as of a specific date or an average of values calculated over a specified period.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h7-h8-2" marker="2.">
              <title type="keyterm">Index beyond creditor's control.</title>
              <content>Index beyond creditor's control. A creditor may increase an adjustable interest rate pursuant to § <ref target="1004-4-a-2-i" reftype="internal">1004.4(a)(2)(i)</ref> only if the increase is based on an index that is beyond the creditor's control. For purposes of § <ref target="1004-4-a-2-i" reftype="internal">1004.4(a)(2)(i)</ref>, an index is not beyond the creditor's control if the index is the creditor's own prime rate or cost of funds. A creditor is permitted, however, to use a published prime rate, such as the prime rate published in the Wall Street Journal, even if the creditor's own prime rate is one of several rates used to establish the published rate.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h7-h8-3" marker="3.">
              <title type="keyterm">Publicly available.</title>
              <content>Publicly available. For purposes of § <ref target="1004-4-a-2-i" reftype="internal">1004.4(a)(2)(i)</ref>, the index must be available to the public. A publicly available index need not be published in a newspaper, but it must be one the consumer can independently obtain (by telephone, for example) and use to verify the annual percentage rate applied to the <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref>.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1004-A-h7-h9" marker="">
            <title>4(c) Requirements for High-Cost and Higher-Priced Mortgage Loans</title>
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h7-h9-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Prepayment penalties.</title>
              <content>Prepayment penalties. If applicable, creditors must comply with <ref target="CFR:12-226-32" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.32</ref>, including <ref target="CFR:12-226-32" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.32</ref>(d)(6) and (d)(7) which provide limitations on prepayment penalties. Similarly, if applicable, creditors must comply with <ref target="CFR:12-226-35" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.35</ref>, including <ref target="CFR:12-226-35" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.35</ref>(b)(2), which also provides limitations on prepayment penalties. However, under § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref>, <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State laws</ref> regarding prepayment penalties are not preempted. See comment 1004.3-3.i. Accordingly, creditors must also comply with any <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State laws</ref> regarding prepayment penalties unless an independent basis for preemption exists, such as because the <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State law</ref> is inconsistent with the requirements of Regulation Z, 12 CFR Part 226. See <ref target="CFR:12-226-28" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.28</ref>.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1004-A-h7-h10" marker="">
            <title>4(d) Other Applicable Law</title>
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h7-h10-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Other applicable law.</title>
              <content>Other applicable law. Section <ref target="1004-4-d" reftype="internal">1004.4(d)</ref> permits <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">state</ref> <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditors</ref> that do not seek preemption under § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref> and federal <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditors</ref> to make <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> consistent with applicable <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">State</ref> or federal law other than § <ref target="1004-4-a" reftype="internal">1004.4(a)</ref> through <ref target="1004-4-c" reftype="internal">(c)</ref>. However, § <ref target="1004-4-d" reftype="internal">1004.4(d)</ref> does not exempt those <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditors</ref> from complying with the provisions of federal law that are incorporated by reference in § <ref target="1004-4" reftype="internal">1004.4</ref> and are otherwise applicable to the creditor. Specifically, nothing in § <ref target="1004-4-d" reftype="internal">1004.4(d)</ref> exempts a <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditor</ref> from complying with <ref target="CFR:12-226-5" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.5</ref>b, 226.32, 226.34, or 226.35.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </appendixSection>
      </appendix>
    </content>
  </part>
</regulation>
